<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>SOPHIE&#39;S WORLD</title>
    <description>What I&#39;m writing when I&#39;m not coding &amp;ndash; or the other way around.
</description>
    <link>http://sbchou.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://sbchou.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 14:40:22 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 14:40:22 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Merry Christmas and a Happy New Year</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/test-cake.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;TEST CAKE&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two pieces today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2015/12/25/opinion/moments-of-grace-in-a-grim-year.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; with your morning coffee and cake-- it&#39;s Christmas Day, and whether you celebrate or not, you need something sweet because you deserve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, when you&#39;re fully caffeinated and ready to face the New Year and the end of civilization as we know it, read &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/11/10/learning-how-to-die-in-the-anthropocene/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Learning to Die in the Anthropocene&lt;/a&gt;.&quot; Sometimes, you need to look down into the abyss-- I promise that you&#39;ll still have to go to work tomorrow. So it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Dec 2015 12:17:24 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://sbchou.github.io/musings/philosophy/2015/12/25/merry-christmas-and-a-happy-new-year.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sbchou.github.io/musings/philosophy/2015/12/25/merry-christmas-and-a-happy-new-year.html</guid>
        
        <category>christmas day</category>
        
        <category>roy scranton</category>
        
        
        <category>musings</category>
        
        <category>philosophy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Portraits and Encounters</title>
        <description>&lt;subtitle&gt;A REVIEW OF THE GAY TALESE READER&lt;/subtitle&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gay Talese’s father was a tailor and his son continues on in his craft: stitching, not with thread but with words, in the same meticulous detail. “The Gay Talese Reader: Portraits and Encounters”, published in 2003 but consisting of selected works between 1961 and 1997, spans the most illustrious part of Talese’s career. Every piece in the collection reads as colorfully as a short story, but sprinklings of detail (“New Yorkers blink twenty-eight times a minute”), along with autobiographical pieces in the latter half (“Origins of a Nonfiction Writer”) remind the reader that this is, in fact, an anthology of nonfiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talese’s presence is never intrusive, but always firm. He hints at the implication of marital disputes and the arthritic hands of Frank Sinatra alike with no mercy. It is a reminder that he views his role as a reporter as one of a craftsman: there to form an image of someone else, but not without imparting his own opinions. This more subjective approach is trademark of the New Journalism of the 1960s and 70s that Talese is credited for pioneering, though he maintains that “it is founded in old-fashioned legwork.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some portraits, Talese’s exceptional attention to detail and mastery in what he calls the “Art of Hanging Out” shines. There are several standalone classics in “The Gay Talese Reader”, most prominent among them “Frank Sinatra Has a Cold”, which was first published in Esquire in 1966 and still hailed as “the greatest literary nonfiction story of the 20th century” 40 years later in Vanity Fair. Never once exchanging a word with Sinatra, Talese nonetheless paints a vivid portrait of Ol’ Blue Eyes, as a performer, a son, a father, and above all Il Padrone, the Italian-hearted boss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These sorts of figures— private, powerful (whether through physical means or art), often on the downfall and above all, masculine, are the personalities that Talese excels at describing. Tales of renowned Italian Americans (Sinatra, DiMaggio) mesh with stories of his own father as an apprentice in the old country (“The Brave Tailors of Maida”), and Talese’s upbringing in New Jersey, learning the fine art of listening from his mother’s dress shop. Indeed, there is a fragment of Talese in each person he chooses to profile. “I never wrote about anyone for whom I did not have at least a considerable measure of respect,” he writes. As a collection, these brief windows into the lives of others piece together a portrait of the author himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In “Portraits and Encounters,” Talese does his best work in chipping away at the masculine psyche. At times he leans Freudian: Marital status is almost always a key to cracking into his subject’s public personas. Comparing past wives to current ones (“Joe Louis: The King as a Middle-Aged Man”) and noting the annoyance Cuban leader Fidel Castro causes Teófilo Stevenson’s wife in misremembering her (“Ali in Havana”), Talese uses wives and mothers (and sometimes beloved daughters, Nancy Sinatra) as foils to the often silent subject. The male gaze is ever-present: women are “blonde”, “brunette”, “petite”, “pleasingly plump”, “curvesome”, “sleek”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rare piece in which Talese enters a female-driven world, “Vogueland” (1960), wades on the surface of a model’s psyche, and it is clear that he is observing from a distance. Other stories also show signs of age: the closing piece, “Walking my Cigar”, is one of the most recent of his writings (1992) yet feels the most archaic. An ode to a seven-dollar cigar, written by a journalist clothed in his impeccably tailored three-piece, is a weak denouement to a masterful collection of stories of immigrants and underdogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, there is no doubt that Talese is a beautiful writer, and his handiwork is to be admired, even in stories that show their age in terms of gender and race. His elevation of everyday details into objects of great fascination achieves the goal that he set out to do at 25: capture the true essence of an era, even if the era that Talese is most tied to is one of the past.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://sbchou.github.io/2015/12/01/talese.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sbchou.github.io/2015/12/01/talese.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Shining the Spotlight on Matt Carroll</title>
        <description>&lt;subtitle&gt;AN INTERVIEW WITH A PULITIZER-PRIZE WINNING BOSTONIAN&lt;/subtitle&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Journalists on film are usually portrayed as idealists or cynics, crusaders or parasites. The reality is much grayer, and more than just about any other film I can think of, ‘Spotlight gets it right.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— A.O. Scott, the New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since its release on November 6th, Spotlight, a movie about the Boston Globe’s 2002 investigation of sex abuse in the Catholic Church, has gathered significant acclaim from the press, with hints of an Oscar nomination. “It’s not a stretch to suggest that ‘Spotlight’ is the finest newspaper movie of its era,” writes Ann Hornaday of the Washington Post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not often that reporters are portrayed by glamorous A-list stars: Mark Ruffalo, Michael Keaton, Rachel McAdams, Liev Schreiber, and John Slattery (the Hulk, Batman, Regina George, Sabretooth, and Roger Sterling, respectively). So it’s fitting that the self-proclaimed “geek” and fourth member of the Spotlight team is portrayed by a Broadway actor, Brian d’Arcy James, that’s barely a household name.  Matt Carroll, lifelong Bostonian, is still in search of the next big thing— Dunkin’ Donuts coffee cup in hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In real life, Carroll is not as shy as his portrayal onscreen, described as “a quiet family man with a mournful mustache” in the New Yorker . Perhaps to his convenience, though, this allows him to skip some press events while staying in character. Spectacles around his neck, coffee in mug, Carroll is always running &lt;em&gt;somewhere&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s wry and humorous, with a Boston accent that emphasizes his no-nonsense speech. Carroll is, in many ways, the quintessential Bostonian: He’s loyal to the Red Sox, honors his father’s work ethic, and draws out the long “a” in Park Street, where the church he attends every week is located. Raised in the Boston area, he went to school at Northeastern University, worked for the Boston Globe for 26 years, and is now settled in West Roxbury with his wife of 32 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion was a large part of his large family growing up (Carroll was the oldest of 18 siblings). In addition to attending the local church every Sunday, the children went to Catholic elementary and high schools. His aunt was a nun. “It’s a very common story for Irish kids my age.”
Still, most “Irish kids” didn’t grow up to expose major corruption in the Church, win a Pulitzer Prize for the investigation, and leave the institution subject to ongoing global scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Carroll is a local and a family man, he’s also a persistent reporter. He began writing for the local paper in high school, and temporarily dropped out of Northeastern to start his own local paper, the Post. At the time, “there was this resurgence of starting good community newspapers.” Together with his friend, and funded by his friend’s brother, the two lasted almost a year running every aspect of the paper, from writing articles to delivery. “It was good,” Carroll said. “We just ran out of money.” He jokes that if he’d invested in a house then, he’d be retired by now. “But instead I wasted it all on a newspaper.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carroll’s knack for reporting is reflected in the way he speaks: every question that’s handed to him is already being directed into the next one, the bigger finding. His savvy with numbers and spreadsheets led him to become the “database reporter” for the Globe, extracting stories out of records and statistics long before the era of Nate Silver and “Big Data.” It was this ability to extract patterns from data that eventually revealed the systematic coverup of clerical sex abuse cases in Boston.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We used those databases as the heart of the story, the nut of the story, the hard kernel of truth,” he said. Lead by Carroll’s initial foray, the team discovered a tactic to uncover potential suspects by looking through the Church’s own annual directories. Entries where priests took frequent “sick leaves” followed by relocation turned out to be a very strong signal for abuse coverup. Carroll and his colleagues went through 20 years worth of books, circling names, and typing them into spreadsheets. “[I]t was unbelievably boring, incredibly laborious, and there were a lot of false positives.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the tedious work paid off. Upon publication, the story rapidly reached global importance as it echoed in parishes around the world.  Eventually, more than 70 priests were uncovered locally using Carroll’s tactic. By the following year, the Archbishop of Boston, former Cardinal Law, was forced to resign. It was by far the most significant story in his career. “This one, it was like riding the back of a tiger, it just took off so fast and so hard, and did not stop for a long, long time.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time Carroll began reporting, he’d already drifted away from Catholicism. But he says that he was and is the only regular church-goer among the team. Speaking candidly about his Catholic upbringing, Carroll doesn’t fixate on the psychology of individuals, only on the failings of the system. Growing up, “everyone knew that there were bad priests, because there’s bad people everywhere, that’s just how it is.”  (He never uses the words “child molester,” always “bad priest.”)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, Carroll is frank about the emotional toll of reporting so close to home. During the investigation, he discovered that one of the accused priests, John Geoghan, lived around the corner from his home. In the movie, this detail is altered. “They thought it wasn’t believable if it was his picture I put on my fridge,” said Carroll, to warn his children, who were ages 8-14 at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investigating the story became so stressful that Carroll created an alter ego. Waking up at 5am each day, he wrote fiction under the pseudonym Sean Patrix before facing the demands of the day. The genre? Horror. Carroll published two e-books, “The Druid” and “The Called,” on Smashwords, a free publishing platform. He has not written fiction since. “Eh, I kinda got that bug out.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[“Something had been sleeping under Lake Champlain for centuries. Something dangerous and best left asleep”]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, Carroll left his home at the Globe, and for the first time in 30 years, he is no longer a reporter. He misses the newsroom, but the slow change of pace at publications in an unstable digital age left him feeling antsy.“You see, the industry is going through tremendous turmoil and I had some ideas for helping out.” Carroll cites the importance of the Internet in breaking the Spotlight team’s story. “It was the last great enterprise newspaper story, and the first great Internet newspaper story.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, at MIT, he runs the Future of News, an initiative that seeks to use creative technologies to push newsrooms “ahead aggressively” in this era of information overload and undependable income streams. These days, instead of hunting for stories, Carroll hunts for technologies that could make stories, and make them big. Alexis Hope, a former student at the Center for Civic Media, is currently advised by Carroll for her storytelling start-up, FOLD. The publishing platform seeks to make complex ideas easy to understand with virtual, linked index cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“He brings decades and decades of hard earned expertise from being on the ground,” said Hope. “He just cares so much about journalism.” She adds that Carroll also provides business insight on how to navigate the news industry in a shifting, virtual landscape. He’s been a keen observer of how the internet impacts storytelling since the early 90s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So many of Carroll’s concerns boil down to business— specifically, the business of funding news. His hopes for Spotlight are that it gives a new emphasis to investigative journalism, particularly that it’s worth paying for. He estimates that team of four, working on the story for five months, cost the Globe a million dollars at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, that’s what he wants to come out of his time at MIT, now that he’s made his mark in the field. What’s the next big project for Matt Carroll, now that he’s earned his Pulitzer and likeness on the silver screen? At this question, he finally parts with his coffee cup. With a hint of a smile, he pounds his fist on the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’d like to be part of the project that saves the news industry across the world by finding a way of minting gold coins for newsrooms.”&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://sbchou.github.io/2015/11/30/mattycarroll.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sbchou.github.io/2015/11/30/mattycarroll.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Shining the Spotlight on Matt Carroll</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My newest writing piece: &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/mattycarroll&quot;&gt;a profile&lt;/a&gt; on Pulitzer-winning data reporter, coffee-addict and Bostonian Matt Carroll!  His story is being told in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/spotlight_2015/&quot;&gt;Spotlight&lt;/a&gt;, a movie that has rave reviews and is in theatres now.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2015 17:20:22 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://sbchou.github.io/journalism/prose/2015/11/29/shining-the-spotlight-on-matt-carroll.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sbchou.github.io/journalism/prose/2015/11/29/shining-the-spotlight-on-matt-carroll.html</guid>
        
        <category>data journalism</category>
        
        <category>FOLD</category>
        
        <category>matt carroll</category>
        
        <category>spotlight movie</category>
        
        
        <category>Journalism</category>
        
        <category>prose</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>true diversity means the whole structure has to change</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There are people whom I admire and then there are people for whom every moment I spend with them, I want to soak up every possible molecule of being in their presence. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/06/arts/dance/06kour.html?pagewanted=all&quot;&gt;Tai Jimenez&lt;/a&gt; is one of those people. Her dance class can only be described as a spiritual experience, because the focus is never on just the steps, but the &lt;i&gt;intent&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;purpose&lt;/i&gt; of every step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And &lt;i&gt;that&lt;/i&gt; is what ballet should be all about. It should be a artistic and introspective &lt;i&gt;life-long&lt;/i&gt; practice, just like yoga or meditation, because it is a beautiful and thoughtful practice. In reality, this is just about the polar opposite of how things tend to go down: even in the small beans non-professional no-name classes I go to, bitches be fightin’ for the barre, and everyone is feeling extra fat in their tights today. It’s a hierarchy of competition and insecurity that dissuades people and stifles creativity, even though the medium is so ripe for creation. Not always, of course, but often enough that it’s always a shadow chasing close behind the joy of movement.  On a larger scale, this feeling works in tandem with existing institutions that reward people of a certain build, skin color, class, and attitude, not always for the best results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;(This is often how I feel about the tech industry and academia as well.)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway. Tai, who also writes, posts a great response on her blog to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Martins&quot;&gt;Peter Martin&lt;/a&gt;, the chairman of the School of American Ballet (SAB), when he asks her to join a new “diversity initiative” for the SAB. As the all-too-frequent token girl / token minority in many lab settings past, present, and future, to whom all the “women in tech”, “minority”, “gender”, and “diversity” inquiries are directed, I can relate to her frustration. Her response is gold:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;“I have been giving the matter of whether or not to join the Diversity Committee some thought. With all due respect, if the School of American Ballet is serious about diversifying, they can start by hiring me as a ballet teacher. I am great.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;This is not about me, and it is about me. Please tell Peter Martins that true diversity means the whole structure has to change. Is he ready for that?”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a follow-up blogpost, she explains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;“My approach to teaching ballet is too different from theirs. They want to create dancers. I want to create an ecstatic moment of dancing. They teach one to master a certain style and technique. I teach dance as a tool for self-mastery. They teach people how to squeeze themselves into a certain look. I teach people how to love themselves as they are and to dance from there. They promote an ideal. I expose the myth. They teach competition. I foster community. They teach hierarchy. I restore sovereignty of self. They pick favorites. I acknowledge everyone’s medicine and stir it up good.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;And sometimes, I play hip-hop. SAB ain’t ready for this jelly.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read her original posts &lt;a href=&quot;http://taijimenez.com/2015/04/28/letter-from-peter-martins-and-my-response/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://taijimenez.com/2015/05/25/follow-up-to-the-peter-martins-letter-and-a-special-offer/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. And, if you’re in the Cambridge/Boston area, definitely, definitely take a class with Tai! She teaches at  Harvard (the classes are open registration) and I believe &lt;a href=&quot;http://jndance.com/classes/&quot;&gt;Jeanette Neil&lt;/a&gt;’s.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2015 11:38:04 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://sbchou.github.io/dance/2015/07/24/true-diversity-means-the-whole-structure-has-to-change.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sbchou.github.io/dance/2015/07/24/true-diversity-means-the-whole-structure-has-to-change.html</guid>
        
        <category>ballet</category>
        
        <category>diversity</category>
        
        <category>tai jimenez</category>
        
        
        <category>dance</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Living in Holland</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eight days before my twenty-third birthday, I embarked on what can only be described as a truly magical journey to three completely contrasting cities: Reykjavik, Amsterdam, and Prague. Along the way, I met a number of fascinating characters-- some of them related to me. Here is an excerpt of my great aunt&#39;s life, which she handed me a photocopy of on my way to the airport leaving Holland. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;* note: &lt;a href=&quot;https://readfold.com/read/mpetitchou/a-completely-unbiased-autobiography-by-my-great-aunt-lenore-eTKBD32N&quot;&gt;interactive version&lt;/a&gt; cross-posted on FOLD, a new publishing platform made by some friends @ the Media Lab.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Living in Holland&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(a completely unbiased autobiography&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;written by my great-aunt Lenore&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for the AWCA)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I am Cantonese but was born in Shanghai, then and now the most cosmopolitan city of China. Already at birth I was touched by the American brush. Both my parents had studied in the States, my dad receiving degrees from MIT and Case Institute and my mom from Columbia University.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There were seven of us, four girls and three boys. I was ‘sister three’… and we were naughty. One day, to give you an example, our gardener was taking a nap, snoring with his mouth open and we put a spoonful of salt on his tongue. My mom scolded us… severely I might add.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After the happy years trouble came, first, the Japanese occupation and then, finally, the communist takeover. We had to flee and since my dad was Minister of Transportation, he had the use of a government plane and we escaped by flying to Taiwan just in time. This all happened a few months before I was supposed to graduate from high school. Fortunately the government in Taiwan granted my diploma, which enabled me to go study in Michigan.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I enrolled at Michigan State University and turned into a party girl, within the limits of decency. Although I didn’t study too industriously, I succeeded in becoming a member of Pi Mu Epsilon (mathematics honorary), Iota Sigma Pi and Sigma Delta Epsilon (chemistry honoraries).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After obtaining my MS in Physical Chemistry I was ready for the world. But was the world ready for me? I decided they and I were going to find out, but in a somewhat warmer climate than Michigan. Go West young woman! I descended upon innocent Seattle (those were the days) and by my first day I had fond a small apartment and a job at the Analytical Department of the University of Washington. All I needed was a husband. So, I spent my weekends dancing and dating (Sleepless in Seattle). The Chinese boys didn’t want me. They want their women, demure, soft-spoken and obedient. A loud-mouth like me was out of the question. So, I had to turn to other prey. At the foreign students club, Cosmo, I cornered Jack Wiegman, a student at the School of Communications, and made him my husband, like it or not.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After he graduated, we moved to New York, where I found a job at my mom’s alma mater, Columbia University. After only one year, out of the blue, I was approached by American Cyanamid, Princeton, NJ, who invited me to an interview and then offered me a position as a research chemist. I succeeded to invent two chemical processes. My boss quickly put his name to one and the other one I was forced to sell for the generous sum of one dollar.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My husband was transferred to Amsterdam and so I was back at point zero. I decided to interrupt my career by having a son. However, when he was two and an intelligent big boy, I felt he was ready for kindergarten and, for me, it was time to resume my career by joining a division of the Dutch Akzo Chemical Corporation in Amsterdam. To put it mildly: I didn’t like it at all. Fortunately, after almost two years, opportunity struck by way of an ad for a position as a research chemist at the Dental Materials Science Department of the University of Amsterdam. Thanks to my work in the States I was chosen among 40 candidates to become Hoofdmedewerker which you could roughly translate as Associate Professor. This you could call the turning point of my life. I came up with two more inventions but— it’s an old story— the head of the department tried to usurp the credit. I fought all the way to the Board of the University and won, but, of course, I had to move. I joined the Electrochemistry Department where I started in a PhD program. In 1979, I obtained the degree with the thesis “The Kinetics of the Hydration of Calcium Sulfate Hemihydrate and Cement, investigated by an Electrical Resistance Method”. (Wow)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To complete the bragging: I am listed in the Marquis Who’s Who in Science and Engineering (US) and also in the International Biographical Centre (Cambridge, England). I also have been a long-time member of the ACS (American Chemical Society).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Six years ago I suffered a stroke. Since then I’ve been confined to a wheelchair.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Now, I have time to catch up on reading and to play with my grandchildren who live in the same building, a canal house on Keizersgracht. And then, of course, there is the AWCA of which I have been a member 29 years.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2015 21:34:08 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://sbchou.github.io/musings/prose/2015/07/09/living-in-holland.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sbchou.github.io/musings/prose/2015/07/09/living-in-holland.html</guid>
        
        <category>amsterdam</category>
        
        <category>family</category>
        
        
        <category>musings</category>
        
        <category>prose</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Post-Barbeque Blues</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Post-Barbeque Blues&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 13px;&quot;&gt;NOW the daffodil is beheaded&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    and floating in her vase;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;MAY has sunk into our bones.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;     tortilla chips &amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;         beer &amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;         burnt sausages&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;fight with strawberry ice-cream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;     on red Solo cups.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;a restlessness halfway between&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;     play &amp;amp; EXHAUSTION:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;         our skin is hot, but&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;         now the air is cold.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;the little girl will go home&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;     &amp;amp; refuse her dinner &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;         just as surely as WE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;         are HOPELESS to do anything but&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;             crawl into the sheets sun-drunk /&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;             on soccer-sweat;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt; listen to tapes of Jack Kerouac&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;     spin tales of desolation angels&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                 subterranean blues&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                 jazz&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: &#39;Tibetan Machine Uni&#39;;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                 &amp;amp; wine.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2015 18:05:16 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://sbchou.github.io/poetry/2015/05/05/post-bbq-blues.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sbchou.github.io/poetry/2015/05/05/post-bbq-blues.html</guid>
        
        <category>bbq</category>
        
        <category>indentation</category>
        
        <category>poetry</category>
        
        <category>summer</category>
        
        
        <category>poetry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>the challenges of large-scale ethical gender identification</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.sophiechou.com/2014/our-machines-our-selves/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, I lamented a bit the potential for advanced technologies to reinforce existing biases at a quicker and larger scale, without either our awareness nor consent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue of algorithmically detecting gender that I briefly mentioned is one that I&#39;ve been struggling with this semester. Inferring gender can be crucial in revealing lags at publications and harmful disparities in behavior where diversity data is not provided, yet the act of classification can be morally and socially harmful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://natematias.com/&quot;&gt;Nathan Matias&lt;/a&gt; is a Ph.D student at the neighboring Civic Media Lab who has been a great ally in helping soften the steep learning curve of grad school and also in tackling gender/identity related projects. His master&#39;s thesis work in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.knightfoundation.org/grants/20120284/&quot;&gt;Open Gender Tracker&lt;/a&gt; has led to many great posts on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/profile/nathan-matias+news/datablog&quot;&gt;the Guardian&#39;s Datablog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like a truly great friend, he not only answered my questions with regard to ethically detecting gender, he wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://civic.mit.edu/blog/natematias/how-to-identify-gender-in-datasets-at-large-scales-ethically-and-responsibly&quot;&gt;comprehensive blogpost&lt;/a&gt; about it. He highlights the practical realities of keeping work both computationally effective and ethically responsible. A must-read for anyone considering work in this area. Thank you Nathan!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 21:29:32 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://sbchou.github.io/data%20science/2014/10/22/the-challenges-of-large-scale-ethical-gender-identification.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sbchou.github.io/data%20science/2014/10/22/the-challenges-of-large-scale-ethical-gender-identification.html</guid>
        
        <category>data science</category>
        
        <category>gender detection</category>
        
        <category>Media Lab</category>
        
        
        <category>data science</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Our Machines, Our Selves</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the seminar I&#39;m taking in Race and Racism, we examined the historical origins of race-- smirking at 19th century attempts to neatly classify and digest mankind into square boxes of color, things like &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Friedrich_Blumenbach&quot;&gt;Blumenbach&lt;/a&gt;&#39;s 5 categories (Caucasian, Mongolian, Ethiopian, American, Malay) and his offensive descriptions of the capabilities of each, how misguided they were, how clearly politically incorrect they are to us now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One image stands out in particular-- a chart, on the left axis, the races; on the right, a marking in each category of human competence, such that, summing up the checked boxes, one might literally rank different humans against another by racial category. The White man wins, in every grouping. It&#39;s a glaring embodiment of early racist ideology, printed on paper, long since dismissed. It would be improbable to imagine a chart like that printed in a 21st century publication; the author would be fired, no doubt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the chart seemed eerily familiar to me. At first I couldn&#39;t place it; I hadn&#39;t seen it before. Then I realized: what it reminded me of was my own education, not in sociology or anthropology, but in Computer Science. As a graduate student, with a focus on Machine Learning and social applications, the very core of many of the algorithms I study and write is &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Statistical_classification&quot;&gt;statistical classification&lt;/a&gt;, a major topic of research. What we are doing now-- what Google does with its personalized search, what Facebook does with its unsettlingly accurate ads-- is automating that same thought process of 19th century anthropologists. We look at a person, here, her technological imprint on the web, the traces she leaves, her purchase history, friends, and log-ins, then say: “what sort of human being are you”? And then, using our charts and tables-- no longer printed ones, but weights on variables in our algorithms and databases of records-- we first classify her, and after, yes, we rank her (sometimes we rank her first and then classify her, as well). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users are commonly classified by gender, or what a machine can predict your gender to be, often quite accurately, and yes, different genders are ranked very differently. In the goods-driven world of online advertisement, a woman is worth differently than a man depending on what the product is, sometimes more, sometimes less. This entire pipeline is problematic to say the least; first, in the binary classification of gender; and then, in the ranking of different gendered individuals against one another; but our algorithms only reflect the constructs already driving these approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Algorithms don&#39;t quite yet classify users by race, or at least not outloud, because race is such a charged issue in most countries. But that doesn&#39;t mean that when an algorithm doesn&#39;t label a category outright, it doesn&#39;t profile users. Algorithms, which learn, much like humans, based on history, only reinforce existing social constructs wherever they are used, because that is what they do: digest data, find a pattern, and make predictions according to that pattern. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/02/05/online-racial-profiling_n_2622556.html&quot;&gt;Harvard Professor Latanya Sweeney&lt;/a&gt; discovered that searches for racially-associated names were disproportionately causing targeted ads for criminal background checks and records to appear. These searches could go beyond offensive because targeted ads are reinforced by user behavior; if I click on that ad, I tell the machine that it was effective in targeting, reinforcing prejudiced thinking. Automated selection processes, which are beginning to gain popularity, such as automated admissions to schools and credit ratings, could cause real, harmful, physical ramifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&#39;t to say that there is anything inherently “evil” in Machine Learning itself; it&#39;s a fascinating field of study, and could become a major tool in public health, disaster relief, and poverty alleviation. The machine is doing nothing new in its actions; it is merely a force multiplier of human behavior.  I believe that classification is core to human cognition; and yes, we label others upon contact, always.  Whether we like it or not, there is no way to escape being classified and classifying others. It&#39;s impossible to meet someone without assigning some kind of underlying worth to them; it sounds ugly out loud, but our classification are essentially value-laden in order to be useful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, our machines only reflect our selves: it is vital to realize that computers are human, raised on human values, and there is no such thing as &lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10676-010-9233-7&quot;&gt;objective computation&lt;/a&gt;. The question that remains is: what kind of value systems will we feed our algorithms? &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2014 19:09:50 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://sbchou.github.io/data%20science/philosophy/race%20and%20racism/2014/10/17/our-machines-our-selves.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sbchou.github.io/data%20science/philosophy/race%20and%20racism/2014/10/17/our-machines-our-selves.html</guid>
        
        <category>algorithms</category>
        
        <category>ethics</category>
        
        <category>machine learning</category>
        
        <category>racism</category>
        
        
        <category>data science</category>
        
        <category>philosophy</category>
        
        <category>race and racism</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>everyday sexism in STEM</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stemfeminist.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Go here now, read and weep&lt;/a&gt;. To people who think that sexism in STEM is just hype, let me tell you that unfortunately, I have *NEVER* worked in a single lab or workplace of a technical nature where I have not experienced some sort of sexism-- ranging from inappropriate comments to outright harassment. That is right-- not a SINGLE lab or company. I would say my resume contains places people would consider inspiring, cutting edge, and liberal. Please be respectful and think about that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hattip &lt;a href=&quot;http://mathbabe.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@Mathbabe&lt;/a&gt; !&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2014 18:56:58 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://sbchou.github.io/feminism/nerdery/2014/10/02/everyday-sexism-in-stem.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://sbchou.github.io/feminism/nerdery/2014/10/02/everyday-sexism-in-stem.html</guid>
        
        <category>feminism</category>
        
        <category>sexism</category>
        
        <category>STEM</category>
        
        
        <category>feminism</category>
        
        <category>nerdery</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
